Guide to the Gaess Outdoor Advertising Photographs, 1950s-1960s and undated RL.00428
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gaess Outdoor Advertising photographs
1950s-1960s and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gaess Outdoor
RL.00428
2.4 Linear Feet
Gaess Outdoor was a family-owned outdoor advertising company founded in the 1930s in northern New Jersey, serving the New Jersey-Metropolitan New York market. It was acquired in 1997 by Universal Outdoor, a subsidiary of Clear Channel Communications, Inc. The Gaess Outdoor Advertising Photographs collection spans the decades of the 1950s and 1960s and includes black-and-white photographs and negatives of painted and blank billboard structures, locations, proposed locations and competitors' billboards. Clients include Budweiser (Anheuser-Busch), Cities Service (Citgo), Gulf Oil, Schaefer and Schlitz. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
3000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, researchers are requested to limit access requests to the photographs. Access to negatives will be permitted only upon consultation with a reference archivist.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gaess Outdoor Advertising Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008.
Historical Note
Gaess Outdoor was founded in the 1930s by "Billy Goat" Gaess, a sign and rock painter in Palisades, N.J. Headquarters later moved to Montvale, N.J. The company maintained billboard structures in northern New Jersey and Westchester County, N.Y., and produced printed and painted billboards as well as electrical spectaculars. It remained a family-owned business until around 1988, when it was purchased by James McAndrew, who operated the company until it was sold to Universal Outdoor, a subsidiary of Clear Channel Communications, in 1997.
Collection Overview
The Gaess Outdoor Advertising Photographs collection spans the decades of the 1950s and 1960s and includes black-and-white photographs and negatives of painted and blank billboard structures, locations, proposed locations and competitors' billboards. Clients include Budweiser (Anheuser-Busch), Cities Service, Gulf Oil, Schaefer and Schlitz.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged into two series: Photographs and Negatives, alphabetically therein. Categories--Advertisers, Dead Files (former clients), Locations, Proposed Locations, Competitors--reflect the original arrangement scheme of the photographs. Photographs and negatives were separated for preservation purposes. Original folder titles were retained where possible.
Conditions Governing Access note
Restriction on Access: Researchers are requested to limit access requests to the photographs. Access to negatives will be permitted only upon consultation with a reference archivist.
Related Material
Related material may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Burr L. Robbins Papers
Garrett Orr Papers
Howard Scott Papers
James O'Shaughnessy Papers
John Paver Papers
Robert A. Hamer Papers
Naegele Outdoor Records
Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records
Outdoor Advertising Association of America Archives
Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- History; Advertising, Outdoor -- New Jersey -- History; Advertising, Outdoor -- New Jersey; Advertising, Outdoor -- New York (State); Advertising, Outdoor; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Advertising -- New Jersey -- History; Advertising -- United States -- History; Billboards; Advertising -- New York (State) -- History; Billboards -- New York (State); Billboards -- New Jersey; Bill-posting; Billboards -- United States; New York (State) -- Commerce; New York (State); New Jersey; Advertising -- New York (State); Advertising -- New Jersey; Advertising -- United States; Advertising -- History; Advertising; Advertising, Outdoor -- New York (State) -- History; New Jersey -- Commerce; Negatives (photographic); Photographs; Gulf Oil Corporation; Gaess Outdoor; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Gaess Outdoor; Jos. Schlitz Brewing Co.; Cities Service Gas Company; McAndrew, James R.; Clear Channel (Firm); Anheuser-Busch, inc.
- Photographs, 1950s-1960s and undated, 2 boxes
  - Advertisers
    - Arthur Maisel's Restaurants; E. 344 Route 4 Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Arthur Maisel's Restaurants; River Street, Hackensack, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Bergen Mall; Route 4, Englewood, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Bergen Mall; Rt. 17, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Chrysler; George Washington Bridge Plaza; Fort Lee, N.J.; Danbill Corporation (Box 1)
    - Cities Service (N-4662); Route 4 Englewood, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service (N-5851); Route 17, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service (N-6874); Route 46, Clifton, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service; Highland Park, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Dutch Boy Spectacular; Sayreville, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; 14th and Henderson Street, Jersey City, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Gulf Oil; E 344 Route 4, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Gulf Oil; Rt. 3, Secaucus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - New Brunswick Secretarial School; Albany and George Streets, New Brunswick, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Raritan River Bridge; Highland Park, N.J.; 2 Ground Bulletins facing to Eastbound traffic (Box 1)
    - Reinauer Brothers; River Rd., Lyndhurst, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schaefer; 218 Washington St., Hoboken, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schlitz; 300 Blvd. East, Weehawken, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Tidewater Oil Company; Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
  - Competitors' Signs
    - Albany and George Street; New Brunswick, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service, Route 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service; Linden, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service; Route 1 and 9 at Lincoln Tunnel Exit, Jersey City, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Donald's Sign; Rt. 17 (Box 1)
    - Early Time; Lincoln Tunnel Highway, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Federal Advertising; Rheingold (Box 1)
    - Gaess Outdoor Advertising; Route 17, Lyndhurst, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Neon Metal Shop Pictures (Box 1)
    - Old Forester; Lincoln Tunnel Highway, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 1)
    - O'Mealia; Rheingold (Box 1)
    - O'Mealia; Schaefer, Jersey City, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Route 4, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Rt. 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schenley; Lincoln Tunnel Highway, Weehawken, N.J. (Box 1)
    - United Advertising; Rheingold and Schaefer (Box 1)
  - Dead File
    - 176-182 Badger Av. Newark, N.J.; Corner of Clinton Av. and W. Alpine Street; Robert Inlander; 972 Broad Street, Newark 2, N.J. (Box 1)
    - 483 Broad Street; New Brunswick, N.J.; Roof Bulletin facing to Northbound traffic (Box 1)
    - 483 Broad Street; Newark, N.J.; Facing to Southbound traffic (Box 1)
    - Bond Clothes; Raritan River Bridge, New Brunswick, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Broad Street, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Brown-Forman; Old Forester; Newark Airport, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Cities Service; North Brunswick, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Gallagher and Burton; 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabethtown, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; Market St. and Raymond Blvd., Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Home Fuel Oil; Union City (Box 1)
    - Hotel Edison; Paramus Road, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Imperial; Newark Airport, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Levine Walls; Paterson, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Middlesex Dairy; Rraritan River Bridge, Highland Park, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Ridgewood Motors; Hohokus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Rockland County locations, NY (Box 1)
    - Route 17, Paramus, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Route 46 and Main Street; South Hackensack, N.J.; Maggio Property (Box 1)
    - Ruppert-Elizabeth (Box 1)
    - Ruppert-Knickerbocker; 1028 Broad Street at Clinton, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Ruppert-Knickerbocker; Rts. 6, 9W, 46, Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schaefer; 789 Broad Street and Market, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schaefer; Newark Airport, Newark, N.J. (Box 1)
    - Schenley; 483 Broad Street, Newark, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Schlitz; Newark Airport, Newark, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Three Feathers; Route 4, Hackensack, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Tollgate Motel; George Washington Bridge Plaza, Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Tydol; George Washington Bridge Plaza, Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 2)
    - U.S. Realty and Investments; Broad Street, Newark, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Wonder Bread; Route 4, Paramus, N.J. (Box 2)
  - Locations
    - 218 Washington St., Hoboken, N.J.; Wall facing to Northbound traffic (Box 2)
    - 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabeth, N.J.; Roof bulletin facing to Southbound traffic on Rt. 1 at traffic circle (Box 2)
    - 789 Broad St. at Market, Newark, N.J.; Roof bulletin facing to Southbound and Westbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Cities Service (N-5849); 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabeth, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Cities Services; 2800 Columbia Av., North Bergen, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Gulf Oil, Fort Lee, N.J.; New Brunswick Sign (Box 2)
    - Holland Tunnel Entrance, Jersey City, N.J.; Union Terminal Cold Storage Warehouse (Box 2)
    - Kessler; 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabethtown, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Tunnel Highway; Colonial Neon; Facing to Eastbound traffic, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 2)
    - River St., Hasckensack, N.J.; Ground bulletin facing to Northbound Traffic (Box 2)
    - Rote 4, Englewood, N.J.; Roof of Cruiser Sales, Facing to Westbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 17, Paramus, N.J.; Ground bulletin facing to Northbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 17, Paramus, N.J.; Ground Bulletin facing to Southbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 4, Englewood, N.J.; Roof of Cruiser Sales; Facing to Eastbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 46, Clifton, N.J.; Facing to North and Eastbound traffic on Rt. 46; Facing to Northbound traffic on Rt. 20 (Box 2)
    - Schlitz; 300 Blvd. East, Weehawken, N.J. (night photos) (Box 2)
  - Proposed Locations
    - Bergenfield, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; Route 4, Englewood, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Tunnel Highway; The Cliff-York Motel Facing to Westbound traffic, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 2)
    - Main Street, Hackensack, N.J.; North of Y.M.C.A (Box 2)
    - McCarter Highway and Broad Street; Newark, N.J.; Facing to Northbound traffic (Box 2)
    - New Jersey Turnpike-Dial Soap Sign; Federal Storage and Warehouse (Box 2)
    - Route 4; Fort Lee, N.J., Facing to Northbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 4; Fort Lee, N.J., Facing to S/E bound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 4; Paramus, N.J.; Facing to Westbound traffic (Box 2)
    - Route 46, Lodi, N.J.; Pace Property (Box 2)
    - Route 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J., Facing to Westbound traffic for Texaco only (Box 2)
    - Route 46, Saddle Brook, N.J.; (Roof of General Supply) (Box 2)
    - Weehawken Stadium; Lincoln Tunnel, Weehawken, N.J. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Loose 5x7 photographs (Box 2)
    - Loose photographs focused around specific building (Box 2)
    - Loose photographs focused on people (Box 2)
    - Loose photographs w/ theme of cigarette companies (Box 2)
    - Loose Pictures (Box 2)
    - Old photographs (Box 2)
    - Providence, Rhode Island; Standish Johnson (Box 2)
    - Route 3, Secaucus, N.J.; Bobbink and Atkins (Box 2)
    - Schlitz (Box 2)
- Negatives, 1950s-1960s and undated, 2 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restriction on Access: Researchers are requested to limit access requests to the photographs. Access to negatives will be permitted only upon consultation with a reference archivist.
  - Advertisers
    - Arthur Maisel's Restaurants; E 344 Route 4, Paramus, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Arthur Maisel's Restaurants; River Street, Hackensack, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Bergen Mall; Route 4, Englewood, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Budweiser; 566 Henderson Street, Jersey City, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Chrysler; George Washington Bridge Plaza, Fort Lee, N.J.; Danbill Corporation (Box 3)
    - Cities Services (N-4662); Route 4, Englewood, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Cities Services (N-5851); Route 17, Paramus, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Cities Services (N-6874); Route 46, Clifton, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Cities Services Tanks; New Jersey Turnpike, Linden, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Cities Services; Highland Park, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Dutch Boy Spectacular; Sayreville, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; 14th and Henderson Street, Jersey City, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Gulf Oil; E 344 Route 4, Paramus, N.J. (Box 3)
    - New Brunswick Secretarial School; Albany and George Streets, New Brunswick, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Raritan River Bridge; Highland Park, N.J.; 2 Ground Bulletins facing to Eastbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Reinauer Brothers; River Rd., Lyndhurst, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schaefer; 218 Washington St., Hoboken, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schlitz; 300 Blvd. East; Weehawken, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Tidewater Oil Company; Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
  - Competitors' Signs
    - Assorted Mounted Color Transparancies (Box 3)
    - Cities Service, Route 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Donald's Sign, Rt. 17 (Box 3)
    - Early Time; Lincoln Tunnel Highway, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Neon Metal Shop Pictures (Box 3)
    - Old Forester, Lincoln Tunnel Highway, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Paramus, N.J.; Various signs owned and maintained by other companies showing cut-outs (Box 3)
    - Rt. 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schenley; Lincoln Tunnel Highway, Weehawken, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schlitz, color film (Box 3)
    - United Advertising; Rheingold and Schaefer (Box 3)
  - Dead File
    - 196-182 Badger Av., Newark, N.J. corner of Clinton Av. and W. Alpine St.; Robert Inlander, 972 Broad St., Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - 483 Broad St., Newark, N.J.; Roof Bulletin facing to Northbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Cities Service; North Brunswick, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Dutch Boy Neon Signs; Colored Pictures (Box 3)
    - Edgebrook Diner; Rt. 1 facing to Northbound traffic, New Brunswick, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; Kingston, NY (Box 3)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; Market St. and Raymond Blvd., Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Home Fuel Oil; Union City (Box 3)
    - Levine Walls; Paterson, N.J. (Box 3)
    - New Jersey Turnpike; Sayerville and Perth Amboy, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Ridgewood Motors; Hohokus, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Rockland County locations, NY (Box 3)
    - Route 46 and Main Street; South Hackensack, N.J.; Maggio Property (Box 3)
    - Ruppert-Knickerbocker; 1028 Broad Street at Clinton, Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Ruppert-Knickerbocker; Rts. 6, 9W, 46, Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schaefer; 789 Broad St. at Market, Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schenley; 483 Broad Street, Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Schlitz; Newark Airport, Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Tollgate Motel; George Washington Bridge Plaza, Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 3)
    - U.S. Realty and Investments; Broad Street, Newark, N.J. (Box 3)
  - Locations
    - 300 Blvd. East, Weehawken, N.J.; Roof Bulletin facing to inbound and outbound traffic at Lincoln Tunnel (Box 3)
    - 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabeth, N.J.; Roof bulletin facing to Southbound traffic on Rt. 1 at traffic circle (Box 3)
    - 789 Broad St. at Market, Newark, N.J.; Roof bulletin facing to Southbound and Westbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Cities Service (N-5849); 725 Edgar Rd., Elizabeth, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Cities Services; 2800 Columbia Av., North Bergen, N.J. (Box 3)
    - E 344 Route 4; Paramus, N.J.; Ground Bulletin facing to Westbound traffic (Box 3)
    - George Washington Bridge Plaza; Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 3)
    - George Washinton Bridge Plaza; Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 3)
    - Gulf Inc.; New Brunswick Sign Co. (Box 3)
    - Gulf Oil; Ft. Lee; New Brunswick Sign Co. (Box 3)
    - Holland Tunnel Entrance, Jersey City, N.J.; Union Terminal Cold Storage Warehouse (Box 3)
    - Lincoln Tunnel Highway; Colonial Neon; Facing to Eastbound traffic, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 3)
    - River Street, Hackensack, N.J.; Ground Bulletin facing to Westbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Route 17; Paramus, N.J.; Ground Bulletin facing to Southbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Route 17; Paramus. N.J.; Ground Bulletin facing to Northbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Route 4, Englewood, N.J.; Roof of Cruiser Sales, Facing to Eastbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Route 4, Englewood, N.J.; Roof of Cruiser Sales; Facing to Westbound traffic (Box 3)
    - Route 46, Clifton, N.J.; Facing to North and Eastbound traffic on Rt. 46; Facing to Northbound traffic on Rt. 20 (Box 3)
    - Schlitz; 300 Blvd. East, Weehawken, N.J. (night photos) (Box 3)
  - Proposed Locations
    - Bergenfield, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Gulf Oil Corp.; Route 4, Englewood, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Gulf Oil, Route 46; Ridgefield, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Hudson River-Palisades; Shakarshian (Box 4)
    - Lincoln Tunnel Highway; The Cliff-York Motel; Facing to Westbound traffic, North Bergen, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Main Street, Hackensack, N.J., North of Y.M.C.A (Box 4)
    - Market Street and Raymond Blvd.; Newark, N.J. (Box 4)
    - McCarter Highway and Broad Street; Newark, N.J.; Facing to Northbound traffic (Box 4)
    - New Jersey Turnpike-Dial Soap Sign; Federal Storage and Warehouse (Box 4)
    - Route 4, Fort Lee, N.J.; Facing to Northbound traffic (Box 4)
    - Route 4, Fort Lee, N.J.; Facing to S/E bound traffic (Box 4)
    - Route 4, Paramus, N.J.; Facing to Westbound traffic (Box 4)
    - Route 46, Lodi, N.J.; Pace Property (Box 4)
    - Route 46, Ridgefield Park, N.J.; Facing to Westbound traffic for Texaco only (Box 4)
    - Route 46, Ridgefield, N.J.; Raymond Flain (Box 4)
    - Route 46, Saddle Brook, N.J.; (Roof of General Supply) (Box 4)
    - Westchester County Airport; West Plains, N.J. (Box 4)
  - Miscelaneous
    - 4 and R Chrysler (Box 4)
    - Bergen Mall; Route 4; Englewood, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Billy Gaess (Box 4)
    - Bridge Plaza; Ricata Building (Box 4)
    - Budweiser; Girl with Book campaign (Box 4)
    - Calvert Reserve; New Brunswick Sign; Christmas Copy (Box 4)
    - Calvert; Calvert Reserve, Good as Gold! (2 bottles) (Box 4)
    - Calvert; Newark Airport; (Gauntlet and hand) (Box 4)
    - Chrysler-New Brunswick Sign; New Lower Price Range-Chrysler Newport (Box 4)
    - Esso Signs; Newark, N.J. 12-15-68 (Box 4)
    - Four Roses; 1963 June 19 (Box 4)
    - Gaess; Fort Lee, N.J. (Box 4)
    - Geo Martin-Gaess (Box 4)
    - Halsey Street; Fur Shop (Box 4)
    - Loose negatives focused on alcohol (Box 4)
    - Loose negatives focused on individuals (Box 4)
    - New Brunswick Sign (Box 4)
    - New Brunswick; Chrysler Bridge (Box 4)
    - New York Skyline (Box 4)
    - Old Cavert, Clear Heads Agree it Tastes Better (Box 4)
    - Original Calvert Reserve (Box 4)
    - Providence, Rhode Island; Standish Johnson (Box 4)
    - Schlitz (Box 4)
    - Schlitz; Blonde Girl with scarf on her head (Box 4)
    - Texaco, 1 color negative (Box 4)
    - Tidewater Oil Company, The Best Refinery, Makes the Best Gasoline (Box 4)
    - Tidewater Oil Company, Now! Super Premium Costs Less! (Box 4)
    - Tidewater, Now! Super Premium (Box 4)
    - Tidewater; Newport Airport; Man and girl (Box 4)
    - Traveler's Sign; Rt. 46 (Box 4)
    - Union Terminal Cold Storage; Photos of Wall- Jersey City, N.J. (Box 4)